

Email
Homepage
LinkedIn
R⁶ Research Gate
GitHub

PROFILE

I am a self-motivated, hardworking, and responsible person who can adapt to all challenging situations. I am motivated by research and able to work well both in a team environment and as well as using my initiative. My research interests include signal and image processing, computer vision, and machine learning with several publications.

EDUCATION

University of Maryland, College Park

2021-Present

Ph.D. in Electrical and Computer Engineering Current GPA: 3.58/4.0

University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka

2015-2020

B.Sc. in Electrical and Electronic Engineering

GPA: 4.0/4.0 (**Top** of the class)

(The complete degree program was conducted and assessed in English medium and accredited by Washington Accord)

2012-2014

Kingswood College, Sri Lanka

G.C.E. Advanced Level (Mathematics, Physics, and Chemistry) (Ranked in the **TOP 20** overall in the country)

PUBLICATIONS

CONFERENCE PAPERS

Convolutional Autoencoder for Blind Hyperspectral Image Unmixing
 Nov 2020
 D.Y.L. Ranasinghe, S. Herath, H.M.H.K. Weerasooriya, E.M.M.B Ekanayake, G.M.R.I Godaliyadda, H.M.V.R. Herath, M.P.B. Ekanayake

 15th Conference on Industrial and Information Systems (Presenter)

Multispectral imaging for automated fish quality grading
 J. M. V. D. B Jayasundara, R. M. L. S Ramanayake, H. M. N B Senarath, S. Herath, G.M.R.I Godaliyadda, H.M.V.R. Herath, M.P.B. Ekanayake
 15th Conference on Industrial and Information Systems

- Transmittance Multispectral Imaging for Edible Oil Quality Assessment
 Jun 2020
 H.M.H.K. Weerasooriya, H.M.S Lakmal, D.Y.L. Ranasinghe, W.G.C. Bandara, H.M.V.R.
 Herath, G.M.R.I Godaliyadda, M.P.B. Ekanayake, T. Madhujith
 Imaging and Applied Optics Congress, Optical Society of America (Presenter)

JOURNAL PAPERS

Transmittance Multispectral Imaging for Reheated Coconut Oil Differentiation

D.Y.L. Ranasinghe, H.M.H.K. Weerasooriya, S. Herath, M.P.B. Ekanayake, H.M.V.R. Herath, G.M.R.I Godaliyadda, T. Madujith

IEEE Access Jan 2022

Constrained Nonnegative Matrix Factorization for Blind Hyperspectral Unmixing incorporating Endmember Independence

E.M.M.B. Ekanayake, D.Y.L. Ranasinghe, H.M.H.K. Weerasooriya, S. Herath, B. Rathnayake, G.M.R.I. Godaliyadda, H.M.V.R. Herath, M.P.B. Ekanayake *IEEE J. Selected Topics in Applied Earth Observations and Remote Sensing*Nov 2021

Patents

A Multi Spectral Imaging System to Measure Transmittance Spectrum

H.M.H.K. Weerasooriya, H.M.S Lakmal, D.Y.L. Ranasinghe, W.G.C. Bandara, H.M.V.R. Herath, G.M.R.I Godaliyadda, M.P.B. Ekanayake.

Patent Sri Lanka No: 20936 (accepted) Jan 2022

PROJECTS

COURSE BASED PROJECTS

2017-2018

Color to Sound Mapping Device

Developed a color-to-sound mapping device for visually impaired people. The device was successfully tested on visually impaired students.

Password Protected Locker

2018-2019

Programmed a pic16f873A from scratch using assembly. Received A+ for the project.

FINAL YEAR THESIS 2019-2021

Hyperspectral Imaging for Remote sensing and agricultural applications

Field surveys used for manual lithological mappings are costly and time-consuming. Therefore, applied algorithms on hyperspectral imaging for potential mineral deposit detection. Successfully developed an algorithm to detect limestone in Jaffna, Sri Lanka.

Multispectral Imaging for food quality assessment

Coconut oil is often adulterated with other oils and existing methods to detect adulteration are laborious and time-consuming. Hence, developed an MSI system for coconut oil quality assessment. Was able to detect coconut oil adulteration with high accuracy.

Deep learning for hyperspectral unmixing

Noticed that deep learning has not been utilized extensively for the hyperspectral unmixing problem. Therefore, experimented with deep learning for the hyperspectral unmixing problem. Developed a Deep autoencoder architecture that generates competitive results.

Image Processing for fish quality Assessment

An automated system was not present to detect the fish quality in the Sri Lankan fisheries industry. Teamed up with NARA (National Aquatic Research lab) to develop a deep learning based method for real-time fish quality assessment. Resulted in an android app for real-time fish quality assessment.

AWARDS

- Jane Ephremides Distinguished Endowed Graduate Fellowship
 Awarded to outstanding Ph.D. students in the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering at the University of Maryland in the field of information science and systems

 C.A. Hewavitharana Memorial Prize for the best performance in Engineering 2020
- C.A. Hewavitharana Memorial Prize for the best performance in Engineering
 Awarded to the best student among all fields of engineering in the faculty
- Ceylon Electricity Board Prize for best performance in Electrical & Electronic Engineering

Awarded to the best student in the field of Electrical and Electronic Engineering

- R.H. Paul Prize for Electrical Power & Machines
 Awarded to the best performing student in the electric power and energy related subject courses
- W.M.G. Fernando Prize for Electronic Communications 2020
 Awarded to the best performing student in the Electronic Communications related subject courses
- Prof. E.F. Bartholameusz Endowment Award for the best student project in Engineering Mathematics
 Awarded for the best final year project in the Faculty of Engineering with an
 - outstanding mathematical background
- W.P. Jayasekara Prize for the best student project in Electrical & Electronic Engineering 2020
- Awarded for the best undergraduate thesis in the Department
- Silver Medal-Sri Lankan Physics Olympiad
 Organized by the institute of physics, Sri Lanka.

Organized by the institute of physics, Sri Lanka. 2014

• Devadasan Challenge Trophy for Best All Rounder 2014

Highest school honor, awarded to one student per each class

WORK EXPERIENCE

• Graduate Teaching Assistant at University of Maryland
ENEE222-Elements of Discrete Signal Analysis
ENEE436-Introduction to Machine Learning
Conduct tutorial classes and lab sessions.

- Temporary Instructor at University of Peradeniya Aug 2020- Jul 2021 Conduct tutorial classes on Engineering Mathematics for first-year students
- Volunteer Instructor at University of Peradeniya Jan 2020- May 2020 Conduction of laboratory sessions for the first-year and second-year students
- Engineering intern at Paraqum Technologies, Colombo
 Feb 2019- May 2019

 Application and development of several signal processing algorithms for a biomedical project and development of standalone GUI programs

COMPETITIONS AND EXTRA-CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES			
COMP	PETITIONS		
•	1st Place-aces Hackathon	2018	
	ACES, Faculty of Engineering, University of Peradeniya		
•	1st Place-Innovators	2016	
	Inventors' Club, University of Peradeniya.		
•	4th Place-aces Coders v6.0	2016	
	ACES, Faculty of Engineering, University of Peradeniya		
•	Best props Manager at Runner-up stage drama	2019	
	Ceylon Dramatic Society, University of Peradeniya		
VOLUNTEERING			
•	Mathematics and Science Instructor	2016,2017	
	Workshops organized in Kandy, Ratnapura, and Badulla		
•	Volunteer – shuttle service	2022	
	Coordinated the picking up and dropping off of students from th	e airport to the	
	campus.		
SPORTS			
•	1st Runner-up	2009	
60615	All Island School Games-Chess.		
SOCIE		2012 2014	
•	Vice President	2013-2014	
	Science Society and Astronomical Society, Kingswood College	2016 2010	
•	Member Drama Society and Music Society University of Peradenive	2016-2019	
•	Drama Society and Music Society, University of Peradeniya Board Member	2022 D	
•	ECE Graduate Student Association, University of Maryland	2022-Present	
WORK	(SHOPS		
VVOIN	NSF ASI-2022	2022	
	Represented the University in a 2-week NSF-funded workshop o	2022 n the theme of	
	Industrial Risk Management held in France.	ii die dielle of	

SKILLS	
Programming	Python, MATLAB, C/C++, Assembly
Libraries	Keras, TensorFlow, Pytorch, Scikit-learn
Technologies	Git, LLVM, Arduino, Raspberry Pi
Design	Proteus, Eagle, AutoCAD
Graphics	CorelDraw, Adobe Photoshop
Type Setting	LaTeX, MS Office
Languages	Sinhalese (native), English (professional)